# Maitraye Das

maitraye.github.io maitraye@u.northwestern.edu

#### **Research Statement**

My research interest sits broadly at the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW), and Accessible Computing, with a focus on studying and designing for accessible collaborative content production in ability-diverse teams, i.e., those involving people with and without disabilities. Methodologically, I take a human-centered, multi-stage approach that involves qualitative studies (e.g., contextual interviews, observations, ethnography) followed by the design, development, and evaluation of new systems through exploratory and mixed-methods experimental analyses. As a first-generation scholar and woman of color from the Global South, my broader goal is to enhance accessibility and inclusion through computing and contribute towards reducing equity gaps in education, employment, and creative work.

# **Education**

#### Northwestern University, Evanston, IL, USA

May 2022 (expected)

PhD in Technology and Social Behavior (Computer Science & Communication)

Dissertation: Augmenting Ability-Diverse Collaboration: Designing for Accessible Collaborative Content Creation by People with Vision Impairments

Committee: Darren Gergle (chair), Anne Marie Piper (co-chair), Marcelo Worsley, and Cynthia Bennett

# Northwestern University, Evanston, IL, USA

Mar 2021

MS in Technology and Social Behavior (Computer Science & Communication)

#### Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

Sep 2015

BS in Computer Science and Engineering (CSE) with Honors

(Top 6% of the graduating class, equivalent to magna cum laude)

Thesis: Protecting Genomic Privacy in Medical Tests using Distributed Storage

Advisor: Tanzima Hashem

# Awards, Honors, & Grants

PhD Student Research Award   Dept of CS, Northwestern University	2021
Graduate Research Grant   Northwestern University (\$2,999)	2021
Best Paper Nomination   ACM ASSETS [C9]	2021
Selected for EECS Rising Stars   Organized by Massachusetts Institute of Technology	2021
Special Recognition for Outstanding Review   ACM CHI (3 times), ACM CSCW (2 times)	2021, 2019
Finalist (top 20)   Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship	2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award   ACM CHI [C8]	2020
Best Paper Honorable Mention Award   ACM CSCW [J2]	2019
Best Paper Award   IEEE COMPSAC [C5]	2018
Student Scholarship   Grace Hopper Celebration, USA	2018
Best Undergraduate Thesis Award   CSE, Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology	2015
Best Technical Poster   Grace Hopper Celebration India [W1]	2014
Student Scholarship   Grace Hopper Celebration India	2014
Dean's List Award   Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology	2011 - 2015
University Merit Scholarship   Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology	2011 - 2014

#### **Journal Articles**

- J5. Maitraye Das, Anne Marie Piper, and Darren Gergle. 2021. Design and Evaluation of Accessible Collaborative Writing Techniques for People with Vision Impairments. In ACM Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI), 42 pages. [Impact Factor: 3.15]
- J4. Maitraye Das, John Tang, Kathryn E. Ringland, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Towards Accessible Remote Work: Understanding Work-from-Home Practices of Neurodivergent Professionals. In Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Vol. 5, CSCW1, Article 183 (April 2021), 30 pages.
- J3. Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, Maitraye Das, and Anne Marie Piper. 2021. Melodie: A Design Inquiry into Accessible Crafting through Audio-Enhanced Weaving. In ACM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS), Vol. 14, 1, Article 5 (March 2021), 30 pages. [Impact Factor: 2.64]
- Q J2. Maitraye Das, Darren Gergle, and Anne Marie Piper. 2019. "It doesn't win you friends": Understanding Accessibility in Collaborative Writing for People with Vision Impairments. In Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Vol. 3, CSCW, Article 191 (November 2019), 26 pages. [acceptance rate: 31.2%]
  Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5% of submissions)
  - J1. \*Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, **Maitraye Das**, Tanzima Hashem, Sharmin Afrose, and \*Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar. 2019. Towards Privacy-preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries. In *Journal of Information Processing*, Vol. 27, (September 2019), pp. 624-642.

# Peer-Reviewed Conference Proceedings Papers<sup>1</sup>

- C10. **Maitraye Das**, \*Thomas McHugh, Anne Marie Piper, and Darren Gergle. [On accessible collaborative writing]. *Under review (title edited to maintain anonymity).*
- Q C9. Kelly Mack, Maitraye Das, Dhruv Jain, Danielle Bragg, John Tang, Andrew Begel, Erin Beneteau, Josh Urban Davis, Abraham Glasser, Joon Sung Park, and Venkatesh Potluri. 2021. Mixed Abilities and Varied Experiences: A Group Autoethnography of a Virtual Summer Internship. In the 23rd International ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility (ASSETS '21), 21 pages. Best Paper Nomination [acceptance rate: 29%]
- **Q** C8. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Weaving by Touch: A Case Analysis of Accessible Making. In *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20),* 1-15. [acceptance rate: 24.3%] **Best Paper Honorable Mention** (Top 5% of submissions).
  - C7. **Maitraye Das,** Brent Hecht, and Darren Gergle. 2019. The Gendered Geography of Contributions to OpenStreetMap: Complexities in Self-Focus Bias. In *Proceedings of the 2019 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '19)*, Paper 563, 14 pages. [acceptance rate: 23.8%]

<sup>\*</sup> Directly mentored student.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup> <u>Top-tier venues in Human-Computer Interaction</u> include extensively peer-reviewed conferences such as CHI. These highly selective conferences are intended for archival papers and <u>comparable to journals in visibility, selectively, and impact</u>. When available, the acceptance rate is included.

- C6. Moushumi Sharmin, Monsur Hossain, Abir Saha, **Maitraye Das**, Margot Maxwell, and Shameem Ahmed. 2018. From Research to Practice: Informing the Design of Autism Support Smart Technology. In *Proceedings of the 2018 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '18)*, Paper 102, 1-16. [acceptance rate: 25%]
- C5. Maitraye Das, \*Nusrat Jahan Mazumder, Sharmin Afrose, \*Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar, and Tanzima Hashem. 2018. A Novel Secret Sharing Approach for Privacy-Preserving Authenticated Disease Risk Queries in Genomic Databases. In Proceedings of the 42<sup>nd</sup> IEEE International Conference on Computers, Software, and Applications (COMPSAC '18), pp. 645-654. [acceptance rate: 24%]

  Best Paper Award
  - C4. Abir Saha and **Maitraye Das**. 2017. Impact of Social Networking on Post-Partum Depression in Women: An Analysis in the context of Bangladesh. In *Proceedings of the 20<sup>th</sup> IEEE International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '17)*, pp. 1-6.
  - C3. **Maitraye Das** and Abir Saha. 2017. An Automated Speech-Language Therapy Tool with Interactive Virtual Agent and Peer-to-Peer Feedback. In *Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Advances in Electrical Engineering (ICAEE '17)*, pp. 510-515.
  - C2. \*Fatema Khan, **Maitraye Das**, and \*Ahiya Ahammed. 2016. PurpleAid: An mHealth platform to combat health hazards of women. In *Proceedings of the 2016 International Conference on Medical Engineering, Health Informatics and Technology (MediTec '16)*.
  - C1. **Maitraye Das**, Sunandita Sarker, and Syeda Lammim Ahad. 2016. A Novel Health Support System with Biometric Data Acquisition Device. In *Proceedings of the 19<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Computer and Information Technology (ICCIT '16)*, pp. 201-206.

# **Lightly Reviewed Publications**

- W8 Maitraye Das. 2021. Designing for Accessible Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. In *Human Computer Interaction Consortium (HCIC '21)*.
- W7. **Maitraye Das.** 2020. Designing for Collaborative Content Creation for People with Vision Impairments. In 2020 Conference Companion Publication on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW '20). [Doctoral Consortium]
- W6. **Maitraye Das,** Katya Borgos-Rodriguez, and Anne Marie Piper. 2020. Rethinking Power and Politics in Accessible Making. In *ACM CHI Workshop "Nothing About Us Without Us": Investigating the Role of Critical Disability Studies in HCI.*
- W5. **Maitraye Das.** 2019. Who Can See What: Privacy and Audience Management for People with Vision Impairments on Social Media. In *ACM CSCW* 2018 Workshop on Addressing the Accessibility of Social Media.
- W4. **Maitraye Das**. 2018. Understanding Collaborative Writing Practices of People with Visual Impairments. In *Proceedings of the 2018 ACM International Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp '18)*, pp. 1744-1749.
- W3. **Maitraye Das**. 2018. Towards Understanding the Effects of Social Networking on Postpartum Depression in Women. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing (GHC)*, USA.

- W2. **Maitraye Das**, Sharmin Afrose, and Tanzima Hashem. 2015. Protecting Genomic Privacy in Medical Tests using Distributed Storage. In *Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing*, USA.
- W1. Maitraye Das, Sunandita Sarker, and Shahina Ferdous. 2014. SpeechAid: A Self-treatment System for Individuals with Speech Disorder. In Grace Hopper Celebration India (GHCI).
  Best Technical Poster Award

# Research Experience

# Northwestern University | Collaborative Technology Lab

Fall 2017 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant | advised by Darren Gergle

- Conducted contextual interviews and observations to understand collaborative writing practices and accessibility needs of blind professionals. Built new accessible systems to support blind writers in asynchronous and synchronous collaborative writing. Evaluated systems through a design exploration study with 15 blind writers and a mixed-methods controlled experiment with 48 blind writers. Faculty collaborator: Anne Marie Piper
- Collected a dataset of nearly 0.45 billion edits by 2000 OpenStreetMap editors using Python and Osmium. Performed quantitative analysis to investigate gender-based self-focus bias in OpenStreetMap. Faculty collaborator: Brent Hecht

# Northwestern University | Inclusive Technology Lab

Spring 2018 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant | advised by Anne Marie Piper

Conducted ethnographic field observations and contextual interviews at a weaving studio for people
with vision impairments. Developed an audio-enhanced loom to support blind weavers in performing
weaving and an audio-tactile system to support accessible designing of fabric patterns.

#### Microsoft Research (MSR), USA | Ability Team

Summer 2020

Research Intern | mentored by John Tang

- Conducted semi-structured interviews with 36 neurodivergent professionals. Outlined practical
  guidelines for inclusive organizational practices and accessible design of remote collaboration tools.
   Faculty collaborators: Kathryn E. Ringland, Anne Marie Piper
- Performed a group autoethnographic study reflecting on accessible practices in an ability-diverse team
  and highlighted opportunities for designing technologies for accessible remote work.
   MSR collaborators: Danielle Bragg, Andrew Begel

# Western Washington University, USA

Summer 2017

Researcher (remote) | mentored by Moushumi Sharmin and Shameem Ahmed

Performed a systematic literature review on smart technologies for children on the autism spectrum.

#### Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology (BUET)

Aug 2014 - Sep 2017

Undergraduate Researcher | advised by Tanzima Hashem

Developed a secret-sharing algorithm for privacy-preserving disease risk queries in genomic databases.

#### **Teaching Experience**

#### United International University (UIU), Dhaka, Bangladesh

Oct 2015 - Mar 2017

Lecturer | Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

Courses: Computer Architecture, Digital Logic Design, Electrical Circuits, Assembly Programming.

### **Course Designed**

Accessible Collaboration | Northwestern University

Mar 2021

Completed as one of the PhD qualifying exams | Supervised by Darren Gergle

 Designed the curriculum of a Computer Science/Communication upper-level undergraduate course on accessibility in collaborative work. Planned class structure, reading materials, assignments, and term projects following the universal design for learning and active learning guidelines.

# **Mentoring Experience**

- Thomas McHugh | Computer Science undergrad, Northwestern University 2020 Present Coauthored paper: [C10]. Own the first place at the ACM Student Research Competition (SRC) at ASSETS 2020 and SRC Grand Finals 2021. Next position: Software engineer at Apple.
- Evan Li | Mechanical Engineering MS program, Northwestern University
   Mentored on designing an audio-enhanced loom for accessible weaving.
- Rawan Mohamed | Computer Science undergrad, Northwestern University
   Mentored on performing qualitative coding on user evaluation data.
- Caroline Brewley | High school student researcher
   Mentored on performing a literature review and design sketching low-fidelity prototypes.
- Dana Choi | Statistics and Economics undergrad, Northwestern University
   Mentored on data labeling for the OpenStreetMap gender bias project.
- Oliver Baldwin | Computer Science and Statistics undergrad, Northwestern University
   Mentored on data labeling for the OpenStreetMap gender bias project.
- Nusrat Jahan Mazumder | Computer Science undergrad, Bangladesh U of Engg. & Tech
   Coauthored papers: [J1] and [C5]. Next position: PhD student at University of Virginia.
- Khandaker Ashrafi Akbar | Computer Science undergrad, Bangladesh U of Engg. & Tech
   Coauthored papers: [J1] and [C5]. Next position: PhD student at University of Texas at Dallas.
- Fatema Khan | Computer Science undergrad, United International University
   Coauthored papers: [C2] and a poster for GHC'17. Next position: Lecturer at Prime Asia University.
- Ahiya Ahammed | Computer Science undergrad, United International University
   Coauthored paper: [C2]. Next position: PhD student at University of Debrecen, Hungary.

#### **Invited Talks, Panels, and Demonstrations**

- Accessibility, HCI, and Aging (AHA) research group | University of Michigan Nov 2021 (scheduled)
   Talk: Designing for ability-diverse collaboration
- Center for Research and Education on Accessible Technology and Experiences (CREATE)
   | University of Washington
   Talk: Designing for ability-diverse collaboration
- Workshop on The Future of Care Work | ACM CSCW
   Discussion topic: Rethinking power and politics in care work within ability-diverse maker communities

•	Microsoft Office and Windows Accessibility Teams   Microsoft Talk: Understanding accessibility in collaborative writing for people with vision impair	Feb 2021		
•	Input and Interaction (INFO 463)   University of Washington Guest lecture: Accessibility in collaborative writing for people with vision impairments Paper [J2] was a required reading for the class.	Nov 2020		
•	New Future of Work Group Meeting   Microsoft Talk: Understanding accessibility in remote work for neurodivergent professionals	Sep 2020		
•	Bangladesh HCI and ICTD Study and Research Group, Virtual Event Talk: Designing for accessible interaction	Apr 2020		
•	PhD Fellowship Finalist Presentation   Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA, USA Poster: Designing for collaborative content creation for people with vision impairment	Nov 2019		
•	TSB Prospective PhD Students Visiting Weekend   Northwestern University Panel discussions on graduate life and research at Northwestern Demonstrations on accessible collaborative writing and weaving	2021, 2018 2019		
Academic Services				
Sha	ogram Committee Member adow PC, ACM COMPASS ace Hopper Celebration, HCI Track	2021 2021		
Re	viewer			
AC	CM CHI [*outstanding review recognitions: 3]	2021		
	CM CSCW [*outstanding review recognitions: 2019, 2021]	2019 - 2021		
	CM Transactions on Accessible Computing (TACCESS)	2021		
	EE COMPSAC	2021		
	EM DIS	2020		
	ace Hopper Celebration	2017		
	stralasian Database Conference	2016		
Stu	ndent Volunteer			
AC	CM CHI	2019, 2021		
AC	CM CSCW	2019		
AC	CM UbiComp	2018		
Inf	oSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University	2018		
Pu	blicity Co-chair			
Inf	oSocial Graduate Conference at Northwestern University	2019		
Οι	itreach & Memberships			
Со	-host & Co-organizer			
	piring Stories (podcast series on Bangladeshi women in STEM)	2020 - Present		
Me	ember			
No	orthwestern Graduate Women in Computing	2019 – Present		
	P	Maitrave Das   p. 6		

Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)	2017 - Present
Special Interest Group on Computer-Human Interaction (SIGCHI)	2017 - Present
Special Interest Group on Accessible Computing (SIGACCESS)	2017 - Present
Bangladeshi Women in Computer Science and Engineering	2015 - Present
Code Coach Volunteer BraveCamp Chicago (non-profit coding camp for high school girls)	Summer 2018
Vice-President Murchhona: BUET (cultural club)	2014 - 2015

# References

# Darren Gergle

John G. Searle Professor

Department of Communication Studies and Department of Computer Science (by courtesy)

Northwestern University.

Email: dgergle@northwestern.edu

# Anne Marie Piper

Associate Professor

Department of Informatics

University of California, Irvine.

Email: ampiper@uci.edu

# Brent Hecht

Associate Professor

Department of Computer Science and School of Communication

Northwestern University.

Email: bhectht@northwestern.edu